<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:cc="http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/rss/creativeCommonsRssModule.html">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Moore Data on Medium]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Exported stories by Moore Data on Medium]]></description>
        <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
        <image>
            <url>https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/fit/c/150/150/1*N732_TvdeFO-1GGO3ZQs2Q.jpeg</url>
            <title>Moore Data on Medium</title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
        </image>
        <generator>Medium</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 21:36:30 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://medium.com/feed/@mooredata" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <webMaster><![CDATA[yourfriends@medium.com]]></webMaster>
        <atom:link href="http://medium.superfeedr.com" rel="hub"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Current Favorite Tools of #MooreData Investigators]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/current-favorite-tools-of-mooredata-investigators-a0fb46f81ad3?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/a0fb46f81ad3</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[data-science]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[python]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[open-science]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 16:10:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-11-08T16:10:22.339Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Carly Strasser</h4><p>You might wonder what it is that Foundation staff do all year (other than <a href="https://media.giphy.com/media/n59dQcO9yaaaY/giphy.gif">swimming in piles of cash like Uncle Scrooge</a>). One of our many activities includes bringing together our grantees so that they can learn from one another — and we can learn from them. We just wrapped up one such event: our 2016 Investigator Symposium. We invited the <a href="https://www.moore.org/initiative-additional-info?initiativeId=data-driven-discovery">14 DDD Investigators</a>, and they brought one lab member each, making the total count of around 30 folks talking about data-driven science.</p><p>As part of this three day meeting, we ask each of the attendees to describe a current favorite tool or method. We (and they) get to hear about the latest interesting technology or software that’s making their lives easier. In the interest of sharing the knowledge, we’ve put this list below with links. Go forth and explore, and of course add tools to the comments that you think are missing!</p><ul><li><a href="http://docs.pyfilesystem.org/en/latest/">Pyfilesystem</a>: simplified common interface to a variety of different filesystems, such as the local filesystem, zip files, ftp servers etc.</li><li><a href="https://slack.com/">Slack</a>: messaging app for teams (especially <a href="https://slack.com/apps/A0F7YS2SX-github">Github</a> &amp; <a href="https://slack.com/apps/A0F7VRDPE-bitbucket">Bitbucket</a> integrations)</li><li><a href="http://dask.pydata.org/en/latest/">Dask</a>: Parallel computing library for Python</li><li><a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/coveralls">Coveralls</a> &amp; <a href="https://coverage.readthedocs.io/en/coverage-4.2/">Coverage</a>: python testing packages</li><li><a href="http://julialang.org/">Julia</a>: high-level, high-performance computing language</li><li><a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/">Rescue Time</a>: time management software</li><li><a href="https://www.typescriptlang.org/">TypeScript</a>: superset of JavaScript that compiles to plain JavaScript</li><li><a href="https://neo4j.com/">Neo4j</a>: native graph database that leverages data and data relationships</li><li><a href="https://workflowy.com/">workflowy</a>: notebook for lists</li><li><a href="https://github.com/ropensci/taxize">taxize</a>: taxonomic toolbelt for R</li><li><a href="https://www.draw.io/">draw.io</a>: drawing program</li><li><a href="http://pydoit.org/">Pydoit</a> package: command line workflow automation. Links to examples and a tutorial available <a href="https://gist.github.com/ctb/124bc83c079ddcaf599fd7e46bf0d626">here</a></li><li><a href="http://www.apple.com/shop/product/MK0C2AM/A/apple-pencil-for-ipad-pro">Apple pencil</a> for iPad</li><li><a href="https://www.crashplan.com/en-us/">CrashPlan</a>: computer backup software</li><li><a href="http://jupyter.org/">Jupyter</a> notebooks</li><li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-organizing_map">self-organizing map</a>: type of artificial neural network</li><li><a href="http://trello.com">Trello</a>: Project management software</li><li><a href="https://www.sharelatex.com/">ShareLaTeX</a>: online LaTeX editor</li><li><a href="https://www.overleaf.com/index_b?utm_expid=71700200-7.jX1xSGOgQzGKvOn08hBHag.1&amp;utm_referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.co.uk%2F">Overleaf</a>: collaborative writing and publishing platform</li><li><a href="https://paperpile.com/">Paperpile</a>: reference management</li><li><a href="http://bokeh.pydata.org/en/latest/">bokeh</a>: interactive visualization library for Python</li><li><a href="https://keras.io/">keras</a>: high-level neural networks library, written in Python</li><li><a href="http://terralang.org">Terra</a>: low-level system programming language that is embedded in and meta-programmed by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lua_(programming_language)">Lua programming language</a>.</li><li>Continuous integration systems for science (see <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/056473">this paper</a> by Beaulieu-Jones &amp; Greene), and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microservices">micro-services</a></li><li><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/checkpoint/index.html">checkpoint</a>: package reproducibility in R</li><li><a href="http://frictionlessdata.io/guides/data-package/">Data Package specification</a> from Open Knowledge International</li></ul><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*nujMd8I1E-daRpayo0ThJg.jpeg" /><figcaption>CC-BY-ND on Flickr by PHIL</figcaption></figure>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Problem Statement: How do we harness data science for new scientific discoveries?]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/b6140bdfd9d?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/b6140bdfd9d</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 18:10:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>1970-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Chris Mentzel and Josh Greenberg</h4><blockquote>This post was derived from opening remarks we made at the <a href="http://msdse.org/summit/">Data Science Summit</a> held on Oct 26, 2016 at NYU</blockquote><p>Today we will explore the role and impact of data science on academic research, in particular, we want to focus on the people — call them data scientists or data-driven researchers — who are making discoveries employing data science techniques in their research areas.</p><p>Across our respective Foundations are a set of research programs that span the life, physical, and social sciences. Had we made this post 5 years ago, we would have started by discussing the “data deluge”, or even “big data” across these fields. Today, this is the only time you see those terms, in this post anyway, and to many of us they sound out-dated.</p><p>But in fact — <a href="http://www.ibmbigdatahub.com/infographic/four-vs-big-data">fast-moving, high volume and high complexity data</a>, continue to disrupt our standard research practices, and continue to overwhelm a large fraction of our research colleagues. One thing has become clear over the last few years, this phenomena is not going away quickly. Yet we see certain labs, certain disciplines, and certain universities leveraging modern scale research data for generating new knowledge of how people, the world, and the universe work.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/869/1*31u90R0Wf9RdcwDXzlt46A.png" /><figcaption>Derived from <a href="https://medium.com/u/de04a04c4ff3">Drew Conway</a></figcaption></figure><p>When we see this kind of data-intensive research success it is generally because those research domains have moved into much closer conversation with computer scientists and statisticians. Further, these collaborations or intersections seem to work best when they are mutually beneficial: with domain research problems motivating advances in computational and statistical methods and theory.</p><p><br>Data science for research is emerging as a convergence of these three areas, from its foundations in computer science and statistics, and its continued innovation and advancement through applications in domains of research and beyond.</p><p>We feel it is essential that when we speak about data science at this early stage of its development, that we include the research domains as an equal partner in its definition. Whether you believe data science is an emerging field of intellectual pursuit, a paradigm shift happening across all of the sciences, or a temporary term that will eventually disappear as technology gets more turn-key, there is utility in keeping its definition in this intersection.</p><ol><li>For one thing, it is clear that data science is having a large and growing impact on all areas of human endeavor. </li><li>We also see that the people who are building up data science in academic research are coming from all three of these broad areas, from the social, life, and physical sciences, as much as from computer science and statistics. </li><li>In addition, it may be that it is the interdisciplinary nature of data science that makes it such a powerful tool for discovery.</li></ol><p>We feel the time is ripe for a dual focus on both the technical advancement of data science for research as well as the academic context of this emerging type of research including, specifically, the challenges and opportunities for the research university. There are many good discussion on the application of data science for research, and in fact many of the research the Moore and Sloan foundations fund take advantage of these new techniques. ((( NEED REFERENCES)</p><p>What seems to be missing from the dialog is: how does one support interdisciplinary data science and data scientists in a modern university? Can university structures and disciplinary definitions of excellence change to accommodate this new kind of research? And how does a modern university compete for talent given the intense demand from industry?</p><p>These questions are at the heart of the <a href="http://msdse.org">Moore-Sloan Data Science Environments</a>. The partners in this endeavor have articulated a few themes, that we think are useful to structure our discussion. They are not the only way to think about data science for research, however, they do provide a straightforward and generally understandable set of topics that almost everyone here is grappling with in some form. </p><ol><li>Career paths for these new types of scientists; </li><li>Software Tools and Methods developed and employed by data scientists; </li><li>Physical and Intellectual Space for collaborations; </li><li>Open and Reproducible Research</li><li>Education and Training for the next generation of data scientists; </li><li>and a self reflective theme around the study and understanding of this emerging practice of data science.</li></ol><p>We wanted to take a moment to call out a theme that is relatively overlooked, and yet seems to be the secret sauce in almost everywhere we have seen with some success around interdisciplinary areas of research: <strong>the physical and intellectual space needed for data science collaborative work</strong>. </p><p>The scientific community has not tired of getting together in person, however, in our day to day lives on campus, dedicated physical spaces, so essential to collaborative work at the intersection of established disciplines, are often hard to come by. By creating a place for people to gather, work together, and bump into each other, we create an environment conducive to greater understanding when we are developing the shared language of data science.</p><p>Some of the work of our colleagues at NYU, UW and Berkeley are looking at this phenomena of collaborative space for data science specifically in a systematic way as part of what they call “Data Science Studies”, and building connections with others around the world who have been looking at team science and interdisciplinary science for years. </p><p>What have you found works with regards to building spaces for data science &amp; interdisciplinary work? Are the themes articulated above the necessary and sufficient set of considerations in building data science for research? Is data science an emerging discipline or an emerging paradigm of science across all disciplines, or both/neither?</p><p>We look forward to exploring these questions with the scientific community!</p><p></p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[If you like free research software, start paying for it!]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/3283c695bab6?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/3283c695bab6</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 09:27:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>1970-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>by Chris Mentzel</h4><h3>***************DRAFT — DO NOT PUBLISH</h3><p>We all like free things, or at least we like when other people pay for things for us. Software for our research is no different, and with the invention of open source software, it seems we have a great solution. Not only is open source software free (as in beer) but its also free (as in speech). What could be better for research than Free Open Source Software (FOSS)? </p><p>One can verify FOSS, opening the blackbox of the code to know how it actually works. One can modify FOSS, making it work better for our and others’ needs. Its perfect for science. Except that it is nearly impossible to sustain for the long term without massive industry support. </p><p>Foundations and Federal funding agencies don’t generally support FOSS projects for the long term. Generally our funding cycles and mandates dictate a 3–5 year horizon for projects that really should like 10–20 years. Much has been said about this cadence mismatch, but that is not my point today.</p><h3>A Marketplace for Research Software</h3><p>At a recent conference on sustainable software for research, the idea of a market place, and appropriate metrics of software quality, came up, again. This idea of a bottom line for services and products that otherwise don’t cost money comes up frequently. In fact in the early days of the Moore Foundation we tried coming up with “outcomes” as the currency of impact for our work. Again, trying to find an analog for cash for those efforts whose results we care about, but which don’t have a way to make money.</p><p>Research software delivers value to its users, at least the codes that are actually used provide value. But we, the science community who use this software, do not feel like we should exchange value with the makers. Why? Well it obvious: it didn’t cost the makers anything to make it, they got a grant to do the work, right? Moreover, the grant came from public funds, likely, and so in a sense, I, as a researcher, have already paid for it through my taxes.</p><p>Making people pay for software also increases friction towards adoption, making getting started even harder. It also goes against the ideal of the free exchange of ideas, given much of scientific software is mainly an implementation of an idea, not a hardened, scalable, or sustainable tool.</p><p>So we dream of a catalog of research software, using complex and imperfect metrics to determine which software is worth using, worth funding, worth it at all. Alternative metrics of impact, beyond usage, beyond contribution of code. We would love to know how our users are using our software, but wont put telemetry into our downloaded software for fear of appearing to “spy” on our fellow scientists. Invasion of privacy is a no-no, though we often left commercial software capture usage data (they also ask), and always let online, hosted software capture our usage without any opt-in.</p><h3>So, you don’t want us to use FOSS for research?</h3><p>Well, not so fast. I am all for FOSS, in fact we help fund a lot of FOSS for many of the reasons mentioned above. I am not abandoning it, but I would like to think about other models or paradigms that take advantage of both FOSS and the commercial software space. A hybrid system.</p><p>We have hybrid systems now, most notably: Freemium. But we also used to use another hybrid system, and that is what I would like to focus on for a moment: shareware.</p><p>Ok, so I just dated myself for mentioning shareware. I had to link it to wikipedia so many of you reading this would know what I was talking about. But bare with me, as shareware offers something different than Freemium, that I think matches the needs of researchers and research software creators, with some small tweaks.</p><h3>Cash or Data, pay what you can</h3><p>Shareware lets the user decide whether they want to pay for the software they are using. It is an honor system, and it likely doesn’t work very well or else we would still see it operating today. Instead we hobble our software, making users pay for “premium” features, and get a cut down version for free. But this wont work for research software, which requires full, unfettered access, including looking under the hood.</p><p> But what if we brought back shareware for research software, with a twist? Offer your FOSS software like you always do, and then indicate that if you use this software, you should pay for it: with cash, with your telemetry usage data, with a paper citation, or all three.</p><p>What I suspect is that at first nothing would change. Think Winzip (((IS THIS RIGHT??))), it always asks you to pay, but never enforces it. But then, a few things will start to sink in to users: 1) they will start equating the opt-in telemetry data with value, in other words, they will start to understand that the developer finds it valuable to understand who, how, and what people are using their software for. 2) They will do better at citing the software they use in their papers (still the dominant form of impact for researchers), and 3) They will start to pay for the software they get the most value from. </p><p>These then all become the indicators of impact we all seek for research software. It becomes a possible sustainability plan for very popular software, and it potentially paves a path forward to how funders can support software development. I know the NIH and others are experimenting with “chits”, where their grantees essentially vote for the software they like/use. An even better chit is cash. Give researchers money to pay for the software they use, and then what do you have: a marketplace. Actually, you just have commercial software, that is also FOSS.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mid-term Evaluation of the Data-Driven Discovery Initiative: Part II]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/mid-term-evaluation-of-the-data-driven-discovery-initiative-part-ii-3c846f27a120?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/3c846f27a120</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[big-data]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[data-science]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 17:19:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-10-13T14:55:21.635Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>by Chris Mentzel</h4><p>A couple of weeks ago, <a href="https://medium.com/@mooredata/mid-term-evaluation-of-the-data-driven-discovery-initiative-part-i-40ae2356c522#.wqtpbqis7">I posted about</a> the origins of the Data-Driven Discovery Initiative, and outlined what we are funding and why. In this post, I dive into the structure of the initiative, our anticipated gains from a mid-term evaluation that’s just beginning, and how that information will feed into a new strategic plan for 2018 and beyond.</p><h3>What is DDD trying to accomplish?</h3><p>The goal of the Data-Driven Discovery (DDD) Initiative is to catalyze shifts towards new norms in academia, where researchers are rewarded for their work in data-driven science, and where new tools and practices for handling large and complex data are widely used. We think these shifts will enable scientists to leverage modern-scale scientific data to drive new types of discoveries.</p><p>To achieve this goal, DDD has three integrated strategies:</p><pre><strong>Institutions Strategy</strong> — Demonstrate innovative organizational structures and activities within academic institutions (“<a href="http://www.msdse.org">Data Science Environments</a>”) which foster data-driven scientists and practices.</pre><pre><strong>People Strategy</strong> — Reinforce data scientists’ value in academia by providing resources to investigators for their labs to practice their innovative, data-driven research.</pre><pre><strong>Practices Strategy</strong> — Drive the creation and dissemination of readily usable and innovative tools, knowledge, and techniques for engaging in data-driven research.</pre><h3>Research Questions for the Evaluation</h3><p>The Moore Foundation’s Measurement, Evaluation, and Learning team has hired Abt Associates to conduct the independent, external evaluation of the DDD Initiative. The external evaluators will study the initiative as a whole, as well as each strategic area, with the following research questions in mind:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*G1FniI3KrYijWqbCh52qmA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Evaluation scaale From Flickr by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/billsophoto/">billsoPHOTO</a></figcaption></figure><ul><li>Thus far, what results has the initiative had, both intended and unintended?</li><li>What has the interplay been among the three strategies, and have they been effective?</li><li>What progress or growth in the data-driven science landscape has DDD’s work most likely contributed to?</li></ul><p>Ultimately, the report from the external evaluators will be published as a public document, and the DDD team will post a response to that report after our Board has made a decision as to what might come next.</p><h3>How will the report be used?</h3><p>The DDD team will combine the evaluation report with our own understanding of the state of the field to synthesize a new strategic plan (see <a href="https://medium.com/@mooredata/mid-term-evaluation-of-the-data-driven-discovery-initiative-part-i-40ae2356c522#.wqtpbqis7">Part I</a> for how we do this). We will also request input from our Science Advisory Board, the academic data science community, and industry data science organizations that intersect with our research community. In other words, like our first plan, any new strategic plan will continue to take advantage of the wisdom of the community.</p><p>The new strategic plan will then be presented to our Board of Trustees who will then determine what’s next for DDD. Under the current time frame this pivotal board meeting will happen in November 2017.</p><p>DDD started from an identified need in the community to support the people and practice of data-driven science. The intent of this mid-term evaluation is to help refresh our understanding of the current needs and identify ways to continue advancing data-driven research in the natural sciences.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fiscal Sponsorship, Hiring Developers, & Tom Waits*]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/fiscal-sponsorship-hiring-developers-tom-waits-81ad42bc6426?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/81ad42bc6426</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[hiring]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[fiscal-sponsorship]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[scientific-software]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[open-source]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 14:46:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-10-13T14:54:44.950Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Carly Strasser</h4><p>Earlier this week I attended a summit of open source software (OSS) projects that are fiscally sponsored by <a href="http://www.numfocus.org/">NumFOCUS</a>. So… what’s fiscal sponsorship and who is NumFOCUS? (If this is old news, skip down to the next section on hiring OSS developers).</p><h4>DETOUR: Fiscal sponsorship &amp; NumFOCUS</h4><p>Fiscal sponsorship is</p><blockquote>a formal arrangement in which a 501(c)(3) public charity sponsors a project that may lack exempt status. This alternative to the projects starting their own nonprofit and allows them to seek grants and solicit tax-deductible donations under the sponsor’s exempt status. — Grantspace.org</blockquote><p>In short, small projects don’t have to go through all the paperwork and effort of getting their own 501(c)(3) up and running — instead they are under the umbrella of an existing not-for-profit organization. This allows the projects to operate with financial assistance from the fiscal sponsor, including providing a means for funders to donate (grant funds) to support the project.</p><p><strong>How this relates to OSS: </strong>Many OSS projects are born in academic settings (e.g., a grad student starts up a cool project). Often the grants that support someone working on that project are run through a PI’s lab at the university. But what happens when the grad student who started the project leaves and wants to keep working on it? If they go on to be a postdoc or PI somewhere, they could continue working on the project by running grants through their new university. But anyone who’s in academia knows that home institutions can change more often than <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Waits">Tom Waits</a>’ voice. More critically — if they instead leave academia, how do they keep that OSS project going? Enter a fiscal sponsor, and in this case, <a href="http://www.numfocus.org/">NumFOCUS</a>.</p><p>NumFOCUS is a 501(c)(3) nonprofit that serves as a fiscal sponsor for OSS, specifically scientific computing software. From their website:</p><blockquote>The mission of NumFOCUS is to promote sustainable high-level programming languages, open code development, and reproducible scientific research. We accomplish this mission through our educational programs and events as well as through fiscal sponsorship of open source data science projects. We aim to increase collaboration and communication within the scientific computing community.</blockquote><p>Here at the Moore Foundation, we support a number of great OSS projects, events, and people through NumFOCUS (including <a href="http://www.datacarpentry.org">Data Carpentry</a>, <a href="https://nteract.io/">nteract</a>, <a href="http://juliacon.org/">JuliaCon</a>, <a href="http://user2016.org/">useR!</a>, <a href="http://csvconf.com/">csv,conf</a>, and tangentially <a href="http://jupyter.org/">Jupyter</a>). This is why I was in attendance at the NumFOCUS Summit this week, which served as an opportunity for folks from many of their supported projects to get together and talk shop.</p><h4>…Back to hiring OSS developers</h4><p>During the Summit, one of the discussions centered around a new <a href="http://www.numfocus.org/blog/numfocus-receives-grant-for-project-sustainability">Sloan-funded project</a> to explore sustainability of OSS projects supported by NumFOCUS. <em>Side note</em>: if this sounds interesting, there’s a <a href="http://www.numfocus.org/blog/projects-director-job-posting">job opening for Projects Director</a>. Tracy Teal (of Data Carpentry fame) led a great session about challenges around sustainability, and Brian Granger (of Jupyter fame) brought up a particularly sticky issue that the <a href="http://jupyter.org">Jupyter Project</a> has been grappling with: <strong>hiring and retaining developers</strong>.</p><p>Of course, hiring developers in general is difficult. Salaries are on the rise, and tech companies are introducing <a href="https://www.jibe.com/blog/recruiting-ideas-5-innovative-talent-acquisition-campaigns-from-2015/">creative strategies</a> to recruit those with coding chops. But Granger brought up an issue very specific to OSS, tied to the fact that much of the work that gets done on OSS projects is on GitHub and viewable by anyone. Essentially the community round OSS is composed of volunteers who are interested in the project and spend some of their “off time” working on software that they feel passionate about. This volunteer pool is a great way to recruit future paid developers on OSS projects, since they understand the software and are already excited about the job.</p><p>The issue is that once these volunteers start making valuable contributions to software projects, tech companies notice — and hire them for salaries two to three times what OSS projects can afford. (here’s an <a href="http://www.socialtalent.co/blog/how-to-use-github-to-find-super-talented-developers">article about tech companies using GitHub as a recruiting tool</a>). As a funder of these projects, I was bummed to hear about this issue. Of course, I’m happy that developers with OS mindsets are joining industry and hopefully taking their love of community projects with them. But that doesn’t help with the real problem Granger brought up: they can’t recruit or retain great developers for OSS projects in this low supply — high demand atmosphere.</p><p>So what’s the solution? It’s not clear. We talked about things like using funds to pay stipends for talented undergrads rather than professional developers, or going the “contractor” route to enable more competitive salaries, but other ideas are welcomed. Ideas about how to connect Tom Waits to fiscal sponsorship are also welcomed.</p><p><em>*The Tom Waits reference is apropos of nothing — it serves as click bait for music lovers and amuses me.</em></p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/1*tm7E_BAJ7TglnkZ4c67v2w.jpeg" /><figcaption>Tom Waits in all his glory, from <a href="https://jlfernandezblog.wordpress.com/2010/11/20/tom-waits-predicando-en-el-infierno/">https://jlfernandezblog.wordpress.com/2010/11/20/tom-waits-predicando-en-el-infierno/</a></figcaption></figure>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mid-term Evaluation of the Data-Driven Discovery Initiative: Part I]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/mid-term-evaluation-of-the-data-driven-discovery-initiative-part-i-40ae2356c522?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/40ae2356c522</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[big-data]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[data-science]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 04:21:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-09-08T14:21:52.662Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Chris Mentzel*</h4><p>The Data-Driven Discovery Initiative (DDD) is beginning a multi-month external evaluation later this month, and the Foundation will share the report and our responses publicly in 2017. We hire professional evaluation consultants to conduct these external evaluations, and have done so for many years for all of its major initiatives. We use their reports to gain independent assessments of progress, challenges, and opportunities, and then develop revised strategic plans accordingly.</p><p>This is the first of a two-part post and will describe the original motivations for funding DDD. In the next post, I will describe the research questions we are focusing on for this “mid-term” external evaluation, and how these questions are linked with our funding choices — or what foundation folk often call “strategies” or “portfolios”.</p><h4>In the beginning</h4><p>The foundation’s history with data-intensive science started with a series of grants made by former Foundation employees John Marchioni, Steve Cheng, Ed Yoon, Jim Omura, and sometimes me (in those early years I weighed in as an IT consultant on some of these projects). We made a series of grants meant to help bridge conservation science with modern (at the time) information technologies. Marchioni coined the term Eco-Intelligence, a clever play on business intelligence (what some call “proto” data science) meets ecological informatics. Building and extending on this work, Jim Omura, David Kingsbury, and I began funding computer clusters, sensor networks, database projects, and other heavy duty technology infrastructure for data-intensive science efforts. These one-off projects were successful, but were always limited in scope as we simply couldn’t support every new lab that began to have these data-intensive needs. Around 2008, David Kingsbury brought me over to the science team full time to begin looking at how we might build a cohesive effort to move things forward.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*8ppg7JVOXCYGDxOrapdp3w.jpeg" /><figcaption>By Katsushika Hokusai (葛飾北斎) — Restored version of File:Great Wave off Kanagawa.jpg Public Domain, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=5576388">https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=5576388</a></figcaption></figure><p>If you recall back to 2008, “big data” was still relatively a new term, as was “data deluge” — with pictures of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Great_Wave_off_Kanagawa">iconic Japanese tsunami print</a> at the front of everyone’s slide deck — <a href="https://hbr.org/2012/10/data-scientist-the-sexiest-job-of-the-21st-century">data science</a> <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/what-is-data-science">wasn’t</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/06/technology/06stats.html?_r=0">sexy</a> yet, and informatics-everything was on the ascendant. We began initially looking at environmental science data, partly because we have a sister program at the Foundation focused on Environmental Conservation. We quickly realized that the challenges of environmental science data were shared by other disciplines and broadened scope to all scientific data.</p><p>Shortly after I started looking into this, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Recession">2009 Great Recession</a> happened, which curtailed new Moore Foundation investments for a while, but also provided time and space for us to dig into the issues surrounding the data deluge in more detail. By 2011 Vicky Chandler was at the helm of the Science Program, the Foundation had renewed purchasing power, and there was a lot more research on a suite of new phenomena sweeping academic research: the popularity of the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Fourth-Paradigm-Data-Intensive-Scientific-Discovery/dp/0982544200">Fourth Paradigm</a> concept, artificial intelligence emerging from its hiatus, and the idea of data-driven research to name a few. We started to see a pattern in groups that were leveraging the data deluge for new scientific discoveries.</p><h4>The rise of the academic data scientist, aka — the data-driven researcher</h4><p>At the center of any lab, department, or other group working with massive, complex and/or fast moving data, there is an individual or tight-knit group that plays an active role in harnessing the information for discovery. These multi/inter/trans disciplinary people and teams are the driving force behind data-driven research, and the tools, methods, and practices of these people are the bedrock for all of modern data science. They are not just computer scientists applying their bag of tricks, though some have deep formal training and accomplishments in CS. They aren’t just natural/social scientists with only enough CS and stats training to be dangerous. They also aren’t just statisticians with a cursory knowledge of domain science. Somewhere in the middle of that <a href="http://drewconway.com/zia/2013/3/26/the-data-science-venn-diagram">now-famous Venn diagram</a> lay data-driven researchers — the key to success for leveraging modern scientific data. I wrote a bit about <a href="https://medium.com/@mooredata/career-paths-for-data-driven-researchers-9bc246cc9f26">career paths</a> for these folks in another blog.</p><p>These data scientists are developing new practices (i.e. methods) that others can use to harness their own data. We think the people and practice of data-driven research need to be recognized as first-class participants in the scientific enterprise. We think they should be rewarded in the same way tools and people in the deep domain silos are rewarded and recognized. And so we set out in 2012 to do just that, to mark a path towards how <strong>institutions</strong> can support data-driven researchers. To shine a spot light on the kinds of <strong>people</strong> who exemplify this new kind of research. Finally, to amplify and stimulate the kinds of <strong>practices </strong>(i.e. tools, techniques, and training) needed to help everyone leverage their data for new discoveries.</p><p>Part II will dive into why we think these three “strategies” or approaches are a good start, and also what we, under our third champion for data intensive science, Dr. Bob Kirshner, hope to learn about our portfolio in the coming months.</p><p>*thanks to Carly Strasser for reviewing and suggesting changes</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Influential References for Data-Driven Research]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/influential-references-for-data-driven-research-54cbe57acc76?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/54cbe57acc76</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[reference]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[data-science]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 19:48:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-08-23T19:54:52.350Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Carly Strasser</h4><p>Back in 2014, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympic_flame">Olympic torch</a> was in <a href="https://www.olympic.org/sochi-2014">Sochi</a> instead of Rio, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=StTqXEQ2l-Y">everything was awesome</a>, and the <a href="https://www.moore.org/initiative-additional-info?initiativeId=data-driven-discovery">Data-Driven Discovery Initiative</a> at the <a href="http://www.moore.org">Moore Foundation</a> was just getting warmed up. We ran an investigator competition to select 14 Data-Driven Discovery Investigators to receive $1.5M each over five years to fund their research. We ended up with a fantastic group that continues to wow me with their achievements, but this post isn’t about them — it’s about what influences researchers like them.</p><p>The Foundation had about ~1100 researchers apply for the investigator awards, and all of them provided a list of up to five “influential works” as part of their application. This provided quite the treasure trove of data on what data-driven researchers think are the most important works for data science. Moore Fellow <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mark-stalzer-97254a">Mark Stalzer</a> and DDD Program Director <a href="https://www.moore.org/people-detail?personUrl=chrism">Chris Mentzel</a> recognized the potential importance of this information, and recently <a href="https://springerplus.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s40064-016-2888-8">published a paper</a> reviewing the works identified by the applicants.</p><p>Stalzer and Mentzel found that out of the nearly 5000 references, there were 53 works that were cited at least six times. Their Table 1 lists the 22 works cited 10 or more times, and could be used as a reading list for an intro data science course. It’s an great mix of works describing tools (<a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022283605803602">BLAST</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PageRank">PageRank</a>), statistical methods (<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1010933404324">Random Forests</a>, <a href="http://projecteuclid.org/euclid.aos/1176344552">Bootstrap methods</a>), and fundamental ways of thinking (<a href="http://www.springer.com/gp/book/9780387310732">pattern recognition</a>, <a href="https://books.google.com/books/about/The_Fourth_Paradigm.html?id=oGs_AQAAIAAJ&amp;source=kp_cover&amp;hl=en">fourth paradigm</a>, <a href="http://store.elsevier.com/Probabilistic-Reasoning-in-Intelligent-Systems/Judea-Pearl/isbn-9781558604797/">probabilistic reasoning</a>). I’ve got big plans to work my way through the list of 22 by the end of 2017 — wish me luck!</p><p>The paper describes how Stalzer and Mentzel clustered the significant works, and provides some insight into broader landscape of the clusters as they relate to data-driven research. It’s an interesting read for anyone thinking about a career in data science, or for those that want to beef up their skills for data-driven research. You can read the <a href="https://springerplus.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s40064-016-2888-8">full article at SpringerPlus</a>:</p><p><em>Stalzer and Mentzel, 2016. “A preliminary review of influential works in data-driven discovery”.</em> SpringerPlus<em> </em><strong><em>5</em></strong><em>:1266. </em><strong><em>DOI: </em></strong><em>10.1186/s40064–016–2888–8</em></p><p>If you want the tl;dr version, I’ve collected a list of the 71 most cited references from the data set here: <a href="http://www.citeulike.org/user/strasser/tag/influentialpapers">http://www.citeulike.org/user/strasser/tag/influentialpapers</a>.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/640/1*iMq372HL7FoYFSd3Rvmjjg.jpeg" /><figcaption>Be inspired! From Flickr by Ian Munroe</figcaption></figure>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Moore Diversity]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/moore-diversity-c59b1f5b88ad?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/c59b1f5b88ad</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[conferences]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 15:06:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-08-03T20:49:17.946Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Carly Strasser</h4><p>Diversity has been on my mind a lot lately. It’s a vague phrase (like “sustainability” or “governance” or “best practices”) — but it’s one that I keep finding myself chatting about with our grantees, fellow conference attendees, and other Moore Foundation personnel. I won’t attempt to cover the gamut of diversity-related topics in this post, however I want to get a few of my more recent thoughts out; this blog post will focus on (primarily gender) diversity at conferences.</p><p>When I say “diversity”, I mean a “variety of characteristics” (h/t Moore legal team). That is, wanting to “increase diversity at conferences we fund” means we want to see more variability in the types of speakers and the people that show up — whether that variability is in their ethnicity, disciplinary background, gender identity, life experience, academic institution, approach to science, etc. Achieving a diverse group of attendees and speakers at a conference rarely happens without intentional effort, and this is especially true for tech-oriented conferences (<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2014/06/23/googles-tepid-plan-to-boost-diversity-at-tech-conferences/">just ask Google</a>). It requires a lot of thought, planning, energy, and an organizing committee who is supportive and committed, and that’s just to think about getting a diversity of speakers.</p><p>Perhaps counterintuitively, one way folks have managed to increase the diversity of speakers at conferences is by anonymizing talk review. <a href="http://bangbangcon.com/">!!Con</a> organizers put out a couple of great blog posts about their efforts to make the conference inclusive, and <a href="http://jvns.ca/blog/2014/05/28/anonymous-talk-submission-equals-amazing/">Julia Evans’ blog post</a> on the benefits of anonymous talk review mentions three big pluses they experienced:</p><ol><li>a diverse range of talks…</li><li>by good mix of experienced and new speakers…</li><li>which were very well presented.</li></ol><p>Julia says that “several people told us that they liked the anonymous review because they were confident they’d be judged fairly on the merits of their proposal. One of our accepted speakers.. told us ‘Thank you so much for [anonymizing everything]! It’s a relief to know that I wasn’t picked for gender, race, age, or anything like that.’ ”</p><p>Anonymizing submissions isn’t a cure-all, however. I was recently at <a href="http://scipy2016.scipy.org/ehome/index.php?eventid=146062&amp;tabid=332930&amp;">SciPy</a>, one of the conferences that <a href="https://www.moore.org/initiative-strategy-detail?initiativeId=data-driven-discovery">DDD</a> supports, and heard several comments about the lack of diversity among attendees and presenters. SciPy does have anonymous submission systems in place, but did not experience the same benefits that !!Con organizers experienced. Read more about this in a thoughtful blog post by <a href="http://www.camillescott.org/2016/07/19/scipy-retrospective/">thoughtful blog post by Camille Scott</a>. This is especially interesting given the successful recent increase in diversity at other Python conferences (e.g., <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_Conference">PyCon</a> sports a 46% female : 54% male ratio for attendees). I take this as more evidence that diversity doesn’t just happen — it takes work.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*-mkhXIGabFm-hkZwFP5nyw.png" /></figure><p>So what should we do? I don’t have a lot of answers, but I’m always looking for ideas. I’m hoping <a href="http://karthik.io/">Karthik Ram</a> will share his experiences with the <a href="http://user2016.org/">useR Conference</a>, which took a proactive approach to diversity that impressed DDD Program Director Chris Mentzel (see his blog post, <a href="https://medium.com/@mooredata/user-2016-a-love-story-8935edd83055#.q7mmxs7k0">useR 2016, A Love Story</a>). PyCon 2015 in Montreal had some great tips on increasing diversity embedded in their <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2015/about/diversity/">diversity statement</a> (note that they actually had a diversity statement!). Some of my other favorite resources: <a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/">Geek Feminism Wiki</a> has a page devoted to <a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Finding_women">women speakers</a> and another on “<a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Finding_women">finding women</a>”. For the ecology and evolutionary biology community, there’s <a href="https://diversifyeeb.wordpress.com/">DiversifyEEB</a> — which highlights women and/or underrepresented minorities in the field. The site’s blogroll points to other similar sites that provide a resource for those looking for speakers in various fields. My fav find was their link to a Pintrest page, “<a href="https://www.pinterest.com/michelleannklin/binders-full-of-women-in-science/">Binders Full of Women in Science</a>”.</p><p>If you’re wondering why all of this matters (other than “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LLk2aSBrR6U">because it’s 2015</a>”), that’s for a future blog post. I plan to summarize the research on why diversity benefits companies, projects, and communities. I’m also thinking about a post devoted to the value and utility of codes of conduct. A more proactive idea is for us to support personnel to assist conferences that we fund in increasing diversity, rather than expecting conference organizers (who are volunteers with limited time) to figure it out… we are looking into this. Stay tuned.</p><h4>Read more</h4><p><a href="https://medium.com/@nmsanchez/diversity-in-tech-faq-v0-1-276e5acd25be#.93x939nn7">Tech diversity FAQ v0.1</a> This is a great resource for the naysayers you might encounter. It might be better titled “Myth Busters: Tech Diversity Edition”.</p><p><a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1002206">Make Gender Diversity in Data Science a Priority Right from the Start</a>, a piece in PLOS Biology by Fran Berman and Phil Bourne.</p><p><a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0160015">Not “Pulling up the Ladder”: Women Who Organize Conference Symposia Provide Greater Opportunities for Women to Speak at Conservation Conferences</a>, published last week in PLOS ONE by Stephanie Sardelis and Josh Drew.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/600/1*bErxAQtcoqJnv5slPyxXgA.jpeg" /><figcaption>A diverse group of speakers and attendees can be a beautiful thing. From <a href="http://blog.manhattantoy.com/">blog.manhattantoy.com</a></figcaption></figure>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[useR 2016, A Love Story]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/user-2016-a-love-story-8935edd83055?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/8935edd83055</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[r-language]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[conference]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[data-science]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 17:10:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-07-12T17:11:10.776Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>by Chris Mentzel</h4><p>I loved the <a href="http://user2016.org/">useR 2016 conference</a>, and here’s why: though I am not a statistician, and I have never programmed in R, I found my first time at this yearly geekfest of R-ficionados to be a friendly, accessible, and instructive event.</p><p>Our program in <a href="https://www.moore.org/science/data-driven-discovery">Data-Driven Discovery</a> focuses on supporting the people and practice of data science for natural science research. Many of the people we support use R, and many others create new approaches to leveraging data for new discoveries through developing new R packages and programs. So it was really about time that one of us here dive into the community of practitioners. It was illuminating.</p><p>First off, this was one of the <strong>friendliest</strong> technology conferences I have ever attended. The normal culture of these kinds of events is lots of looking at your shoes, peering into your phone, or simply plugged into your laptop- working. While there was some of that here too, the breaks and meals were noteworthy in that people introduced themselves, discussed the day’s sessions, or just talked shop around R and stats. It was amazingly easy to break the ice with new people, almost as if useR had its own special culture of meeting new people, built-in.</p><p>The tenor of conversation was <strong>non-dogmatic</strong>. This was an entire conference dedicated to one language, filled to the brim with statisticians, and yet there was an openness to discussing other languages, what other non-R technology they liked, and how R fit within the larger ecosystem of tools. It was refreshing.</p><p>Though I am sure they will release stats on this soon, my sense is that there was a higher than usual level of <strong>diversity</strong> at this useR conference. I’d estimate about 25–35% women attendees, speakers, and 33% of the keynotes. OK, so these are not perfect numbers in the absolute, yet compared to your average tech or computer science conference, it is trending in a better direction. It also seemed that though stats was the dominant discipline, there were a significant number of other research disciplines represented, and certainly the academic/industry split was pretty healthy.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*cSnFjttjPdJDq1u9A4xvmw.jpeg" /><figcaption>#rcatladies — photo credit: <a href="https://twitter.com/SanghaChick">@SanghaChick</a></figcaption></figure><p>Also, I &lt;heart&gt; <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/rcatladies"><strong>#rcatladies</strong></a>, and not just because they now have a hexagon sticker like all the cool kids. It helps to have something like this to bring attention to diversity at a technology conference. Also, cats. (Listen to this <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/not-so-standard-deviations/id1040614570?mt=2&amp;i=352399874">Not So Standard Deviations</a> podcast that explains the origins of #rcatladies).</p><p>Lastly, I loved useR 2016 because the <a href="http://user2016.org/keynotes.html"><strong>keynotes</strong></a> were as informative as they were compelling. Think back to the last time you attended a conference where most of the keynotes were worth attending and actually warranted paying attention. At useR all of the keynotes I attended were good: not only did they have R-oyalty like <a href="http://hadley.nz/">Hadley Wickham</a> of RStudio, but also researchers like <a href="http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~nolan/">Deborah Nolan</a> and <a href="https://faculty.washington.edu/dwitten/">Daniela Witten</a>, as well as a surprise appearance by Stanford’s <a href="http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~uno/">Don Knuth</a>, creator of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TeX">TeX</a>, speaking on literate programming.</p><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">Literate programming</a> actually turned out to be an unexpectedly great idea for this conference. Though it is a relatively old topic, first published about by Knuth in the early 19080&#39;s, it combines the correctness of mathematical thinking with a practical solution for even modern challenges of reproducible research and code. In short, write code for humans to understand, not just the compiler.</p><p>Old things are new again. <a href="http://msdse.org/files/50YearsDataScience.pdf">Stats and Data Science</a>.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*N2UgjBg7i4nNpoGksgOj-w.jpeg" /><figcaption>cc by Chris Mentzel</figcaption></figure>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Conference Scene for Data-Driven Discovery]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/the-conference-scene-for-data-driven-discovery-316a054841b?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/316a054841b</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[conferences]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[big-data]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[data-science]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2016 19:21:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-06-21T19:26:58.312Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Carly Strasser</h4><p>Do you ever get <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear_of_missing_out">FOMO</a> when you see a conference hashtag on Twitter? We do. Luckily, we have a way to find out what conferences are most important to our grantees in <a href="https://www.moore.org/initiative-additional-info?initiativeId=data-driven-discovery">Data-Driven Discovery at the Moore Foundation</a>: annual reports. As part of our yearly fact-gathering from grantees, we request information about the conferences they have attended in the last year. We collected this information from our 14 <a href="https://www.moore.org/initiative-additional-info?initiativeId=data-driven-discovery">DDD Investigators</a> and more than 100 researchers from the <a href="http://msdse.org">Moore-Sloan Data Science Environments</a>, with representatives from many different disciplines, career stages, and methodological approaches. Below is a list of the 30 most attended conferences last year, in alphabetical order:</p><ul><li><a href="http://sigmod2016.org/">American Chemical Society Special Interest Group on Management Of Data (ACM SIGMOD)</a></li><li><a href="https://aas.org/meetings/aas228">American Astronomical Society (AAS) Annual Meeting</a></li><li><a href="https://fallmeeting.agu.org/2016/">American Geophysical Union (AGU) Annual Meeting</a></li><li><a href="https://www.aps.org/meetings/">American Physical Society (APS) Meetings</a></li><li><a href="http://community.apsanet.org/annualmeeting/home">American Political Science Association (APSA) Annual Conference</a></li><li><a href="http://aoir.org/aoir2016/">Association of Internet Researchers (AoIR)</a></li><li><a href="http://astrohackweek.org/">Astro Hack Week</a></li><li><a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/company/d4gx/">Bloomberg Data4Good Exchange (D4GX)</a></li><li><a href="http://esa.org/ftlauderdale/">Ecological Society of America (ESA) Annual Meeting</a></li><li><a href="http://www.cs.rug.nl/jbi/eurovis2016/">Eurovis</a></li><li><a href="http://ieeevis.org/">IEEE VIS</a></li><li><a href="http://icml.cc/2016/">International Conference on Machine Learning</a></li><li><a href="https://www.iscb.org/ismb2016">ISCB: Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology</a></li><li><a href="https://www.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2016/index.cfm">Joint Statistical Meetings</a></li><li><a href="http://juliacon.org/">JuliaCon</a></li><li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Mozfest/2016">Mozilla MozFest</a></li><li><a href="https://nips.cc/">Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)</a></li><li><a href="http://psb.stanford.edu/">Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing</a></li><li><a href="http://www.pycon.org/">PyCon</a></li><li><a href="http://pydata.org/">PyData</a></li><li><a href="http://www.iscb.org/recomb-regsysgen2016">RECOMB Regulatory Genomics</a></li><li><a href="http://scipy2016.scipy.org/ehome/index.php?eventid=146062&amp;tabid=332930&amp;">SciPy</a></li><li><a href="https://www.siam.org/meetings/calendar.php">Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) Conferences</a></li><li><a href="http://www.kdd.org/conferences">SIGKDD: Asociation for Computing Machinery’s Special Interest Group on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</a></li><li><a href="http://www.sicb.org/meetings/2016/index.php">Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology (SICB)</a></li><li><a href="http://www.sts2016bcn.org/">Society for the Social Studies of Science</a></li><li><a href="http://sc16.supercomputing.org/">Supercomputing</a></li><li><a href="http://user2016.org/">UseR</a></li><li><a href="http://vldb2016.persistent.com/">Very Large Data Bases (VLDB)</a></li><li><a href="http://wssspe.researchcomputing.org.uk/">Working towards Sustainable Software for Science: Practice and Experiences (WSSSPE)</a></li></ul><h4><em>A digression: “Why do you require those pesky annual reports?”</em></h4><p>Annual reports are the yearly documents we require from those we fund to better understand their work, as well as its reach and impact. Anyone who’s ever had to submit a report to a funder knows this task can be tedious, but the data and information we collect is vital to helping others (especially our boards, in the case of private foundations) to understand the importance of what our grantees are accomplishing. If all goes well, maybe we can get more money to fund people and projects like you!</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/480/1*wmfr3bpTt098tEtlwcXUyw.jpeg" /><figcaption>fomo is real — it’s a restaurant in Shanghai. From Flickr CC-BY-ND by John Pasden</figcaption></figure>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Open Access Policy for #MooreData]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/open-access-policy-for-mooredata-21f86d70e32f?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/21f86d70e32f</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[publishing]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[open-access]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 14:26:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-06-07T14:26:59.066Z</atom:updated>
            <cc:license>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</cc:license>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Carly Strasser</h4><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/612/1*rKHlMhqTy4H-AFP8w-f5XA.jpeg" /><figcaption>Unlock your research! CC-BY-SA from Flickr by Thomas Ulrich</figcaption></figure><p>Open access to research articles has been in the news quite a bit lately (see the <a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/04/whos-downloading-pirated-papers-everyone">SciHub controversy</a>, the <a href="http://www.nature.com/news/biologists-urged-to-hug-a-preprint-1.19384">preprints in biology discussion</a>, and the European Union’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2016/may/28/eu-ministers-2020-target-free-access-scientific-papers">recent announcement</a>). The <a href="https://www.moore.org/initiative-strategy-detail?initiativeId=data-driven-discovery">Data-Driven Discovery</a> team at the <a href="http://moore.org">Moore Foundation</a> has also been discussing open access, particularly as it relates to the publications generated by our <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/mooredata">#MooreData</a> researchers. Our grantee population is fairly progressive when it comes to open science, and many of the outputs that they generate are already publicly available (including proposals, software, workflows, and publications). It is therefore easy for us to imagine that they would embrace a policy that mandates open access for research articles that they produce. That said, we are always open to discussions!</p><p>Below are sections from a draft DDD policy that we are considering. We would love to have feedback, comments, and discussion from grantees and others. Note that the larger policy will include software, data, and other outputs, but we are not ready to share those sections just yet.</p><h3>Proposed Moore DDD Policy Excerpts</h3><p>The Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation wants to maximize the impact of the research we fund. To this end, Data-Driven Discovery Initiative grantees are expected to provide the widest possible access to their research outputs. This will help promote reproducible research, increase the pace of discovery, and ensure broader societal and economic benefits from the work they do. We welcome comments, questions, and concerns about this policy, and encourage discussion around how best to achieve the goal of broad research impact.</p><h4>Preprints</h4><p><strong>Ideally</strong>, all journal articles would first be available as preprints. Preprints are versions of your manuscript that are not yet peer reviewed. Many journals allow you to submit articles that have been available as preprints (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_academic_journals_by_preprint_policy">this list</a> for more information). Read more about the benefits of preprints <a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001563">here</a>. Typical places where preprints are deposited for free (read more from Jabberwocky Ecology <a href="https://jabberwocky.weecology.org/2014/07/07/which-preprint-server-should-i-use/">blog</a>):</p><ul><li><a href="http://arxiv.org/">arXiv</a> (for physics, mathematics, computer science, quantitative biology)</li><li><a href="http://biorxiv.org/">bioRxiv</a> (for any biology research)</li><li><a href="https://peerj.com/preprints/">PeerJ Preprints</a> (for biology, medical/health sciences, computer sciences)</li><li><a href="https://figshare.com/">figshare</a> (for any research)</li></ul><h4>Publications</h4><p>We <strong>require</strong> that all journal articles resulting from research that we fund be openly accessible. This can be achieved in one of two ways:</p><p><strong>Gold Open Access: </strong>Choosing a journal that has the option to make your article open access at the time of publication (this is known as “Gold Open Access”). Journals that have a Gold Open Access option are listed in the <a href="https://doaj.org/">Directory of Open Access Journals</a>, which also provides fee information for those that require payment for making your article Open Access. Note that <strong>GBMF will pay for your open access fees</strong>; please email us at <a href="mailto:ddd@moore.org">ddd@moore.org</a> for more information.</p><p><strong>Green Open Access: </strong>If the journal does not have an open access option, you should ensure that they have a policy that allows you to post the publication on a secondary site afterward (this is known as “Green Open Access”, or “self archiving”). To learn about a journal’s policy, go to the <a href="http://www.sherpa.ac.uk/romeo/search.php?la=en&amp;fIDnum=%7C&amp;version=&amp;mode=advanced">SHERPA/ROMEO website</a> and search for your preferred journal name. Journals typically allow one of the following, all of which are acceptable options for complying with the policy:</p><ul><li>posting preprint versions only</li><li>posting the final version, but not the journal’s PDF version</li><li>posting the journal’s final PDF version</li></ul><p>You should post whatever version is allowed in a publicly accessible place, ideally a repository with a long term preservation policy (as opposed to a lab website or other more transient location). To find an open access repository, search the <a href="http://www.opendoar.org/">Directory of Open Access Repositories</a> or talk to your institution’s librarian. Many institutions have repositories specifically for archiving Green Open Access manuscripts.</p><p>Sometimes journals require embargoes on your self-archived version; we are open to discussion about whether such embargoes should be allowed (and if they are mandatory, whether a grantee should publish in that journal).</p><p>Still confused about Open Access? Here’s a handy animation from Phdcomics that explains it:</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FL5rVH1KGBCY%3Ffeature%3Doembed&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DL5rVH1KGBCY&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FL5rVH1KGBCY%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=d04bfffea46d4aeda930ec88cc64b87c&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="640" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/5c617d0a7fa7f450442b21bd87a0a058/href">https://medium.com/media/5c617d0a7fa7f450442b21bd87a0a058/href</a></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Like Wellcome’s language on how to comply with their policy (h/t Arfon): https://wellcome.ac.uk…]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/like-wellcomes-language-on-how-to-comply-with-their-policy-h-t-arfon-https-wellcome-ac-uk-1fee37213d96?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/1fee37213d96</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 14:34:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-06-07T14:34:48.659Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Like Wellcome’s language on how to comply with their policy (h/t Arfon): <a href="https://wellcome.ac.uk/funding/managing-grant/complying-our-open-access-policy">https://wellcome.ac.uk/funding/managing-grant/complying-our-open-access-policy</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Career Paths for Data-Driven Researchers]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@mooredata/career-paths-for-data-driven-researchers-9bc246cc9f26?source=rss-ebfbc0fb97f6------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/9bc246cc9f26</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[big-data]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[data-science]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Moore Data]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 14:27:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2016-05-31T14:27:08.264Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>By Chris Mentzel</h4><p>If you get nothing else out of this post, please read <a href="https://twitter.com/jakevdp">Jake VanderPlas</a>’ great write up on this topic, “<a href="https://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2013/10/26/big-data-brain-drain/">The Big Data Brain Drain: Why Science is in Trouble</a>”, and his follow-up, “<a href="https://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/08/22/hacking-academia/">Hacking Academia: Data Science and the University</a>”. Even though they are from 2013 and 2014, they are still extremely valid, and I fear will continue to be so for quite some time.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/500/1*mwpC0QengKoe5wbh7JilwA.jpeg" /><figcaption><a href="http://www.realclear.com/science/2015/12/16/14_revolutionary_inventions_by_women_that_changed_the_way_we_live_12528.html">http://www.realclear.com/science/2015/12/16/14_revolutionary_inventions_by_women_that_changed_the_way_we_live_12528.html</a></figcaption></figure><p>Jake is by no means the lone voice on this topic. In fact there is a growing <a href="http://reportingtexas.com/as-research-funds-dry-up-science-doctorates-make-a-beeline-for-data-jobs/">chorus</a>, not to mention an <a href="http://www.software.ac.uk/">entire organization</a> in the UK, devoted to this topic. I was just at a meeting hosted by the Computing Community Consortium on the topic of “<a href="http://cra.org/ccc/events/computing-innovation-societal-needs-the-impact-of-computing-research/">Computing Research: Addressing National Priorities and Societal Needs</a>”, where a question was asked about how we should support infrastructure or other key science software. My answer centered not so much around funding models, or technology stacks, but rather to start focusing on career paths for the researchers among us who build these essential products and services. You might call these people data-driven researchers (we do) or data scientists, and they are having a difficult time inside academic research right now.</p><p>In speaking about this over the last few years, I have notice that researchers who do this kind of data-driven work are fairly consistent in what they need:</p><p><strong>Intellectual Freedom</strong><br>Data Scientists/Data-Driven Researchers are highly trained and educated scientists, at least in the academic research context, and should be afforded the freedom to choose projects/research they work on. Know when to hire an independent researcher, and when to hire a software engineer. Both are important, and their roles differ in the ability to choose projects.</p><p><strong>Respect / Stability</strong><br>Data Scientists/Data-Driven Researchers, who are not tenure-track faculty, need a path within academia that is well respected and stable (i.e. not just soft money positions). This is a hard nut to crack, as there are very few examples of how to do this well. I like* what is emerging at places like Berkeley, UW and NYU with respect to their <a href="https://bids.berkeley.edu/people?field_people_status_tid_2=49&amp;field_research_areas_tid_selective=All">Computational Fellows</a>, Data Scientist (<a href="http://escience.washington.edu/about-us/people/">Research Staff</a>) and <a href="http://cds.nyu.edu/mooresloan/">Research Engineer</a> roles. If you can’t compete on salaries (<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/2015-data-science-salary-survey">and you can’t</a>), you at least need to get this right.</p><p><strong>A Diverse Community</strong><br>Data Scientists/Data-Driven Researchers should not sit alone in the basement, the sole practitioner in a group. This is an emerging area of study, that is rapidly evolving, and will thrive with a variety of perspectives including different disciplines, genders, cultural and educational backgrounds. The more we share what is working and not working in this space, the faster we will advance.</p><p>One thing you might notice about these items is that they are essentially the attributes that attract people to academia in the first place. Making data-driven researchers an integral part of the science enterprise should be at the front of the priority queue for anyone interested in advancing discovery science.</p><p>*clearly <a href="http://msdse.org/">biased</a> on my part</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>